## Sumanta BOSE

Contact Information 50 Nanyang Avenue

N4-B2b-05, Hardware & Embedded Systems Lab

School of Computer Science and Engineering

Nanyang Technological University

Singapore - 639798

sumantabose@ntu.edu.sg
https://sumantabose.me/

+65 98612535



Research Interests

- Full-stack distributed ledger technology system research, with specialization in blockchain.
- Mathematical modeling and simulation of semiconductor quantum nanostructures.

Work Experience Nanyang Technological University, Singapore

Nov 2017 – Ongoing

Senior Research Engineer Advisor: Prof. K. Y. Lam, Asst. Prof. A. Chattopadhyay 'Cybersecurity Protocol and Mechanism for e-Logistics of Dangerous Goods Tracking Using Blockchain' funded by a ~\$1 million National Research Foundation (NRF) Singapore grant. I work on full-stack distributed ledger technology systems, with specialization in blockchain.

Research Experience

## KdotP Soft., (NTU) Singapore

Aug 2016 – Jan 2017

Software Engineering Intern

\*\*Advisor: Assoc. Prof. Weijun Fan

Worked on the simulation engine, database creation and development of a GUI for KdotP Soft, a scientific software for semiconductor physics and device physics simulation.

Indian Institute of Science (IISc) Bangalore, India

May 2012 – Oct 2012

Research Intern, Microwave R&D Lab

Advisor: Prof. K. J. Vinoy

Worked on delay engineering using cascaded microwave all-pass filters for acoustic imaging by chirp waveforms for application in transmission lines acting as dispersive structures.

Qualcomm Inc., Bangalore, India (Offer Declined)

Summer 2012

Interim Engineering Intern, Corporate R&D Lab

Selected among top 6 students from NIT Trichy. Not pursued due to personal reasons.

National Institute of Technology (NIT) Trichy, India Dec 2011 – Feb 2012 Research Intern, Antennas Lab Advisor: Assoc. Prof. D. S. Kumar Worked on smart-fractals employing algorithms for rapid beam-forming in smart antennas.

Intl. Institute of Information Technology (IIIT) Hyderabad May 2011 – June 2011 Research Intern, VLSI and Embedded Systems Lab *Advisor*: Asst. Prof. S. R. Chowdhury Built an intelligent health security system for automated real-time breath rate tracking.

#### Oil India Limited (OIL), Duliajan, India

 $\mathrm{Dec}\ 2010$ 

Industry Trainee Advisor: Mr. T. N. Madhavan Worked on various electronic/pneumatic instruments and developed a control system model.

Education

Doctor of Philosophy (Ph.D.), Electrical & Electronic Engineering CGPA: 4.63/5.00 Nanyang Technological University (NTU) Singapore 2013 – 2017

Thesis: Semiconductor Quantum Nanostructures for Optoelectronic Applications

 $Advisor\colon {\sf Assoc.}$  Prof. Weijun FAN and Prof. Dao Hua ZHANG

Bachelor of Technology, Electronics & Communication Engineering CGPA: 8.36/10.0 National Institute of Technology (NIT) Trichy, India 2009 - 2013 FYP: Mathematical Modeling of a Metamaterial Regular Polygon Split Ring Resonator

Advisor: Prof. S. Raghavan

#### Skillset

**Programming:** Golang, C++, C/Embedded C, Python, Fortran, Perl, Verilog HDL. Engineering tools/libraries: MATLAB, Origin, COMSOL, OpenCV, NumPy, SciPy.

Blockchain Platforms: Hyperledger Fabric, Ethereum (Solidity), Corda.

Web technologies: NodeJS, HTML, PHP, CSS, JavaScript. Operating systems: Linux, Unix, RTOS, ROS, Windows, DOS.

Firmware development: BLE, NFC, RFID Zigbee, I2C, SPI and UART.

Development platforms: Arduino, Raspberry Pi, Beagleboard, TI Launchpad, FPGAs.

#### Mentoring

#### Nanyang Technological University (NTU) Singapore

Mentor Aug 2015 – Aug 2017 Mentored 2 students in their Final Year Projects (FYPs) on semiconductor simulation.

## Teaching

#### Nanyang Technological University (NTU) Singapore

Language consultant, HG4045 Structure of a Language Spring 2016 - 2017 Recording, transcription, phonemic analysis and documentation of Assamese as a language.

Laboratory assistant, E2004L Digital Electronics

Fall 2016 - 2017

Combinational logic circuits, counter and shift registers, logic circuit simulation.

Teaching assistant, EE1003 Introduction to Materials for Electronics Spring 2015 - 2016Characteristics of semiconductors, biomaterials, smart materials and nanomaterials.

Laboratory assistant, EE1071 Introduction to EEE laboratories Fall 2015 – 2016 Electronic components, working with AC waveforms, soldering and circuit-building.

#### National Institute of Technology (NIT) Trichy, India

Teaching assistant, EC204 Transmission Lines and Waveguides Spring 2012 - 2013 Planar transmission lines, composite substrates and electromagnetic CAD tools.

Teaching assistant, EC307 Antennas and Propagation Spring 2012 – 2013 Microstrip antennas, CNT antennas, metamaterial loaded antennas and wearable antennas.

# Non-affiliated teaching

Maker Faire, Singapore

2015 - 2016

Introduction to Robotics, Arduino, Raspberry Pi, PCB CAD design and 3D printing.

#### Organization TheBlockchainSPIRIT Hackathon

Lead Organizer

Jun 2018

Organized a Singapore wide 2-day blockchain hackathon on leading blockchain platforms -Hyperledger, Ethereum and NEM with 100+ participants and international representation.

#### **TEDxNTU**

Lead Curator

Apr 2016 – Mar 2017

Co-Curator

Apr 2015 – Mar 2016

Involved in the planning and organization of TEDx (Technology, Entertainment, Design) chapter of NTU Singapore. Served as the lead organizer of the TEDxNTU 2016 edition.

#### NTU – World of Wisdom (WOW)

Co-Founder and Vice-Chairman

Apr 2015 – Mar 2017

Involved in the development of a think tank bringing together students and providing them with opportunities to mould their skills in diverse areas of science, economics, arts, etc.

#### NTU - Graduate Student Council (GSC)

Committee Director

Apr 2015 - Mar 2016

Involved in the planning and organization of academic workshops and talks. The flagship event is the 3-minute-thesis (3MT) in collaboration with NTU library, Student Life Office.

#### IEEE Young Professionals, Singapore Chapter

Executive Committee Member

Nov 2015 - Nov 2016

Involved in facilitating young graduates to become world class professionals, enhancing their skills and establishing a diverse professional network, through workshops and networking.

#### Robotics and Machine Intelligence (RMI), NIT Trichy

Head, Electronics division

July 2011 – June 2013

Involved in robotics project including micromouse, line-follower, PIR motion sensor, accelerometer controller. Other projects involved image processing and PID control systems.

# Honors and Awards

- IEEE Region-10 Young Professionals Affinity Group Award in recognition and appreciation of valued services and contributions; Aug 2016.
- NTU Research Scholarship, for the duration of Aug 2013 July 2017
- University Graduate Scholarship, University of Glasgow, offered 2013
- Grant for Student of EUR 750 to present a paper at the 6<sup>th</sup> Intl. Congress on Adv. Electromagnetic Materials in Microwaves & Optics, St. Petersburg,; Sept 2012.
- Govt. of India's University Grant Commission (UGC) Sponsored Fellowship for Summer Research Internship at Indian Institute of Science (IISc), Bangalore; May July 2012.

# Academic Services

#### Talks (Invited)

- 7<sup>th</sup> Annual World Congress of Advanced Materials 2018 in Xiamen, China; Sep 2018.
- 4<sup>th</sup> Annual World Congress of Smart Materials 2018 in Osaka, Japan; Mar 2018.
- 3<sup>rd</sup> Annual World Congress of Smart Materials 2017 in Bangkok, Thailand; Mar 2017.
- EMN Meeting on Optical Communications 2016 in Dubai; Nov 2016.

# Journal Reviewer

- Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE): Journal of Lightwave Technology.
- Institute of Physics (IOP): Materials Research Express; Nanotechnology; 2D Materials.
- Springer Open: Nanoscale Research Letters.
- Multidisciplinary Digital Publishing Institute (MDPI): Computation; Applied Sciences.

#### Conference Reviewer

- IEEE TENCON 2016 IEEE Region 10 Conference
- IEEE CRALT 2016 Conference on Recent Advances in Lightwave Technology

#### Professional Memberships

- Member, Institute for Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE)
- Memberships Member, IEEE Photonics Society
  - Life Member, Society of Electromagnetic Compatibility (EMC) Engineers India, SEMCE(I)

# Media Coverage

- 'NIT-T student gets grant to attend conference on metamaterials', The Hindu, Aug 2012
- 'Young India', a mass broadcast radio program by All India Radio (AIR), Oct 2012

# Citation Indices

Citations: 158h-index: 7

• i10-index: 5

# Thesis Publication

• S. Bose, "Semiconductor Quantum Nanostructures for Optoelectronic Applications", Doctoral Dissertation, Nanyang Technological University Singapore, 2018.

#### Journal Publications

- Y. Liu, S. Bose, W. J. Fan, "Effect of size and shape on electronic and optical properties of CdSe quantum dots", *Optik International Journal for Light and Electron Optics*, **155**, 242-250, 2018.
- S. Bose, S. Shendre, Z. Song, V. K. Sharma, D. H. Zhang, C. Dang, W. J. Fan, H. V. Demir, "Temperature-dependent Optoelectronic Properties of Quasi-2D Colloidal Cadmium Selenide Nanoplatelets", Nanoscale, 9, 6595-6605, 2017.
- S. Bose, W. J. Fan, D. H. Zhang, "Optoelectronics of Inverted Type-I CdS/CdSe Core/Crown Quantum Ring", Journal of Applied Physics, 122 (16), 163102, 2017.
- Z. Song, S. Bose, W. J. Fan, D. H. Zhang, Y. Y. Zhang, S. S. Li, "Quantum Spin Hall Effect and Topological Phase Transition in InN<sub>x</sub>Bi<sub>y</sub>Sb<sub>1-x-y</sub>/InSb Quantum Wells", New Journal of Physics, 19 (7), 073031, 2017.
- S. Bose, Z. Song, W. J. Fan, D. H. Zhang, "Effect of lateral size and thickness on the electronic structure and optical properties of quasi two-dimensional CdSe and CdS nanoplatelets", *Journal of Applied Physics*, **119** (14), 143107, 2016.
- Z. G. Song, S. Bose, W. J. Fan, S. S. Li, "Electronic band structure and optical gain of GaN<sub>x</sub>Bi<sub>y</sub>As<sub>1-x-y</sub>/GaAs pyramidal quantum dots", *Journal of Applied Physics*, 119 (14), 143103, 2016.
- W. J. Fan, S. Bose, D. H. Zhang, "Electronic bandstructure and optical gain of lattice matched III-V dilute nitride bismide quantum wells for 1.55μm optical communication systems", Journal of Applied Physics, 120 (9), 093111, 2016.
- K. Prabu, S. Bose, D. S. Kumar, "BPSK based subcarrier intensity modulated free space optical system in combined strong atmospheric turbulence", *Optics Communications*, **305**, 185-189, 2013.
- M. Levy, S. Bose, D. S. Kumar, A. V. Dinh, "Rapid beam forming in smart antennas using smart-fractal concepts employing combinational approach algorithms", *International Journal of Antennas and Propagation*, vol. 2012, ID 467492, 2012.
- M. Levy, S. Bose, A. V. Dinh, D. S. Kumar, "A novelistic fractal antenna for ultra wideband (UWB) applications", *Progress In Electromagnetics Research B*, **45**, 369, 2012.
- S. Bose, M. Ramaraj, S. Raghavan, S. Kumar, "Mathematical modeling, equivalent circuit analysis and genetic algorithm optimization of an N-sided regular polygon split ring resonator (NRPSRR)", Elsevier Procedia Technology 6, 763-770, 2012.
- S. Bose, S. Delikanli, V. K. Sharma, C. Dang, W. J. Fan, D. H. Zhang, H. V. Demir, "Electronic Bandstructure and Excitonic Absorption in CdSe Nanoplatelets", *Nanoscale*. [under review]
- S. Bose, W. J. Fan, D. H. Zhang, "Optoelectronics of Quasi Two-dimensional  $CdS_xSe_{1-x}$  Nanoplatelets", Journal of Physics D: Applied Physics. [under review]

# Conference Publications

- S. Bose, M. Raikwar, A. Chattopadhyay, D. Mukhopadhyay, K. Y. Lam, "BLIC: A Blockchain Protocol for IC Manufacturing and Supply Chain Management", *IEEE International Conference on Blockchain (Blockchain)*, 2018.
- S. Mitra, S. Bose, S. Sen Gupta, A. Chattopadhyay, "BLAV: Blockchain Protocol for Tamper-resilient and Secure Data Aggregation in Autonomous Vehicles", 14<sup>th</sup> IEEE Asia Pacific Conference on Circuits and Systems (APCCAS), 2018.
- M. Raikwar, S. Ruj, S. Bose, S. Sen Gupta, A. Chattopadhyay, K. Y. Lam, "Security and Privacy of Permissioned Blockchains", 1<sup>st</sup> Workshop on Blockchain and Sharing Economy Applications (BlockSEA), 2018. [progress]

- S. Bose, S. Delikanli, A. Yeltik, M. Sharma, O. Erdem, C. Dang, W. J. Fan, D. H. Zhang, H. V. Demir, "Anomalous Spectral Characteristics of Ultrathin sub-nm Colloidal CdSe Nanoplatelets", Conference on Lasers and Electro-Optics (CLEO), 2017.
- S. Bose, S. Delikanli, M. Z. Akgul, Y. Gao, W. J. Fan, D. H. Zhang, H. V. Demir, "Inverted Type-I CdS/CdSe Core/Crown Colloidal Quantum Ring", Conference on Lasers and Electro-Optics (CLEO)/Europe and the European Quantum Electronics Conference (EQEC), 2017.
- S. Bose, W. J. Fan, D. H. Zhang, "Theoretical Investigations of Excitonic Absorption in Quasi Two-dimensional CdSe Nanoplatelets", 12<sup>th</sup> Conference on Lasers and Electro-Optics Pacific Rim (CLEO-PR), 2017.
- S. Bose, W. J. Fan, D. H. Zhang, "Strain Profile and Size Dependent Electronic Bandstructure of Type-I CdS/CdSe Quantum Ring", 12<sup>th</sup> Conference on Lasers and Electro-Optics Pacific Rim (CLEO-PR), 2017.
- S. Bose, Z. Song, W. J. Fan, D. H. Zhang, "KdotPsoft: Modelling and Simulation of Semiconductors and Device Physics", 9<sup>th</sup> International Conference on Materials for Advanced Technologies, 2017.
- Z. Song, S. Bose, W. J. Fan, X. H. Tang, D. H. Zhang, S. S. Li, "Electronic structure and optical gain of  $InAs_{1-x-y}N_xB_y/InP$  pyramidal quantum dots",  $g^{th}$  International Conference on Materials for Advanced Technologies, 2017.
- T. Chaudhuri, Y. C. Soh, S. Bose, L. Xie, H. Li, "On assuming Mean Radiant Temperature equal to air temperature during PMV-based thermal comfort study in air-conditioned buildings",  $42^{nd}$  Annual Conf. of the IEEE Industrial Electronics Society, (IECON), 2016.
- S. Bose, W. J. Fan, J. Chen, D. H. Zhang, C. S. Tan, "Strain Profile and Size Dependent Electronic Band Structure of GeSn/SiSn Quantum Dots for Optoelectronic Application", International Conference on Fibre Optics and Photonics, 2014.
- S. Bose, W. J. Fan, C. Jian, D. H. Zhang, C. S. Tan, "Strain profile, electronic band structure and optical gain of self-assembled Ge quantum dots on SiGe virtual substrate", 7<sup>th</sup> International Silicon-Germanium Technology and Device Meeting (ISTDM), 2014.
- S. Bose, K. J. Vinoy, "Group delay engineering using cascaded all pass filters for wideband chirp waveform generation", *IEEE International Conference on Electronics, Computing and Communication Technologies (CONECCT)*, 2013.
- K. Prabu, S. Bose, D. S. Kumar, "Analysis of optical modulators for Radio over Free Space Optical Communication systems and Radio over Fiber systems", *Annual IEEE India Conference (INDICON)*, 2012.
- S. Bose, M. Ramraj, S. Raghavan, "Design, analysis and verification of Hexagon Split Ring Resonator based Negative Index Metamaterial", Annual IEEE India Conference (INDICON), 2012.
- S. Bose, S. Raghavan, "Theoretical Investigations of a N-sided Regular Polygon Split Ring Resonator with Skew Rotation", The 6<sup>th</sup> International Congress on Advanced Electromagnetic Materials in Microwaves and Optics, 2012 [accepted, but not presented]
   Awarded 'Grant for Students' - registration fee waiver and travel allowance (EUR 750)
- M. Ramraj, S. Raghavan, S. Bose, S. Kumar, "Elliptical Split Ring Resonator: Mathematical Analysis, HFSS Modeling and Genetic Algorithm Optimization", Progress In Electromagnetics Research Symposium (PIERS), 2012.
- M. Levy, D. S. Kumar, A. Dinh, S. Bose, "A novelistic approach for rapid beam forming in smart antennas for wireless applications using smart-fractal concepts and new algorithm", International Conference on Advances in Mobile Network, Communication and its Applications (MNCAPPS), 2012.
- S. Bose, K. Prabu, D. S. Kumar, "Real-time breath rate monitor based health security system using non-invasive biosensor", 3<sup>rd</sup> International Conference on Computing Communication & Networking Technologies (ICCCNT), 2012.

• S. Bose, K. Prabu, D. S. Kumar, "Array Signal Processing & Optimization using Algorithms in Nature", *International Proceedings of Computer Science & Information Technology*, 2012.

#### References

Dr. Kwok Yan LAM Dr. Anupam CHATTOPADHYAY Dr. Dao Hua ZHANG Professor Assistant Professor Professor School of CSE School of CSE School of EEE NTU Singapore NTU Singapore NTU Singapore KwokYan.Lam@ntu.edu.sg Anupam@ntu.edu.sg eDhZhang@ntu.edu.sg Phone: +65 67905925 Phone: +65 67906092 Phone: +65 67904841

# Personal Particulars

First Name: SumantaFamily Name: Bose

 $\bullet$  Gender: Male

• Date of Birth: January 26, 1990

• Nationality: Indian

• Email: sumantabose@ntu.edu.sg

• Tel: +65 98612535